Guide to the Records of the Office of the Vice Chancellor (C. Duncan Rice) RG.6.1.2
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Vice Chancellor (C. Duncan Rice)
1988-1996
1991-1996
New York University Archives
RG.6.1.2
2.5 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
The collection is made up of the records of C. Duncan Rice created during his tenure as Vice Chancellor of New York University, dating between 1991 and 1996. These records pertain to the administration of the university during that period, with particular emphasis on global initiatives, in line with President L. Jay Oliva's vision of NYU as a fully internationalized university. Many of the materials relate to Rice's efforts to bring internationally-prominent scholars and public figures to the university through such efforts as the International Visitors Program. Rice had also served as the Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences at NYU from 1985-1994. He stepped down from the Dean's position to devote his full efforts to the Vice Chancellorship in 1994. In 1996, Rice left NYU to assume the post of Principal at his alma mater, the University of Aberdeen.
Access Restrictions
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Arrangement
The collection is composed of subject files which are organized alphabetically. This reflects the original order of the files as received by the University Archives. Titles of individual files have likewise been retained. This collection is arranged into one series.
The collection is arranged in a single series of subject files which are organized alphabetically. This reflects the original order of the files as received by the University Archives. Titles of individual files have likewise been retained.
Scope and Content
The collection is made up of the records of C. Duncan Rice created during his tenure as Vice Chancellor of New York University, dating between 1991 and 1996. These records pertain to the administration of the university during that period, with particular emphasis on global initiatives, in line with President L. Jay Oliva's vision of NYU as a fully internationalized university. Many of the materials relate to Rice's efforts to bring internationally-prominent scholars and public figures to the university through such efforts as the International Visitors Program.
Other materials in the collection relate to major donations to the university, relations with individual donors and larger foundations, and the NYU Society of Fellows. Some correspondence provides documentation of John Brademas' activities as President Emeritus. One folder, labeled "Carnegie," contains materials dating from 1988-1991, at which time Rice served only as Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Science. The materials in that folder, however, relate to the previous folder of correspondence between L. Jay Oliva and John Brademas and various representatives of the Carnegie Foundation.
Biography of C. Duncan Rice
C. Duncan Rice was Vice Chancellor at NYU from 1991 until 1996. He was preceded in the office by Debra James. Rice had also served as the Dean of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences at NYU from 1985-1994, when he stepped down from the Dean's position to devote his full efforts to the Vice Chancellorship. As Vice Chancellor, Rice led NYU's global initiatives, part of President L. Jay Oliva's vision of NYU as a fully internationalized university.* Rice left NYU in 1996 to assume the post of Principal at his alma mater, the University of Aberdeen. He was knighted in 2009 for his services to higher education. The Sir Duncan Rice Library at the University of Aberdeen, opened in 2012, is named for him.
Sources:
1. Archives Bio file, C. Duncan Rice; New York University Archives, New York University Libraries 2. "The Sir Duncan Rice Library." The University of Aberdeen. N.p., n.d. Web. 04 Nov. 2013.
New York University |x Administration |y 20th century.; New York University |x Administration.; New York University |x Fundraising
- Series I: Subject Files, 1991-1996; 3 boxes
  - Association of American College & Univesrity Programs in Italy, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Council on Education, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumni/International, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Astor, Marcus, Christensen, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - L. Jay Oliva, John Brademas re: Carnegie Commission, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Carnegie, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CAS Language Coordinating, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Center for Economic Policy Research/Benhabib, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - COIMBRA, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Commission on Internationalized Community, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Commission on the Internationalized Community: meetings, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Manoff, Center for War, Peace, and the News Media, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cross-School Recruitment, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Council for the United States and Italy, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - ERASMUS project, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - European Commission, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Global Public Affairs, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hardin Proposal, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Institute for Education and Social Policy, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - International Visitors Program, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Marc Leland, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Milbank House, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Onassis, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Other Schools, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Papamarkou/Vardinoyannis Gifts, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Alex Ponti, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Presidents File, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Russian House, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Society of Fellows, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Society of Fellows: Bernard Crick's visit, April '96, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Society of Fellows letterhead, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Society of Fellows Budget Stuff, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Society of Fellows, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Society of Fellows: Christine Ockrent's Visit, February '96, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Society of Fellows: Visit by Arthur Chaskalson, April 1997 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Proposed Society of Fellows dinner, March 7, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Technical Conference, Mexico, April 1996, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lillian Vernon Proposal, 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 2)